All right, so today's דף daf is קל"ד, kuf lamed daled, 134.
We pick up on the very bottom of קל"ג עמוד ב'. kuf
lamed gimmel amud beis. I do want to mention two points that
came up yesterday quickly. One is that we had a whole list
of the 24 מתנות כהונה, matnos kehuna, and the middle group, which
is things that were eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, a strange inclusion in
that list was the skins of the קרבנות, korbanot, which even of
an עולה olah is given to the כהנים, kohanim, but we've never
heard that that's limited to eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, like Michael asked
at the very end, I was a little too rushed to respond.
But anyway, when the רמב"ם Rambam lists it, it seems that it
really does not belong in that list, that it's a way of
balancing the fact that on the one hand they got it out
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but it's not limited to the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and on the other hand really could be
eaten anywhere or used anywhere I should say. The רמב"ם Rambam when
he refers to that he says this is a gift that is
בא מן המקדש, ba min hamikdash, but he doesn't say only eaten
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so I want to say maybe it means that
ideally they would keep it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it would be more
respectful. Anyway, that's about the skins of the קדשים. kodashim. The other
thing I should mention, which somebody mentioned yesterday as well, is that
we mentioned the ways in which a female כהן, kohen, a כהנת,
kohenet, has status, and the גמרא Gemara spoke about זרוע לחיים וקיבה.
zeroa l'chayayim v'keiva. רש"י Rashi emphasized the fact that that was because
there was no קדושה kedusha to those things, so the קדושה kedusha
things are things that are more limited to the male כהנים kohanim
and their immediate families, their wives, their daughters who are not married
and so on, but not to a female כהן kohen by virtue
of her own status. And therefore it's logical to assume that that
extends to ראשית הגז, reishis hagez, which the רמב"ם Rambam says, but
then there is and this even if these women are married, because
it's not by virtue of them being part of their father כהן's
kohen house and therefore it's only if they're unmarried, it's by virtue
of them being כהנות kohanos themselves and therefore even if they're married
to non-כהנים, kohanim, even if they're married to ישראל Yisrael as the
גמרא Gemara brought out. And we also mentioned at the time that
the רמב"ם Rambam extends that to a לויה leviyah for the מעשר,
maaser, because מעשר maaser does not have קדושה kedusha and a לויה
leviyah is entitled for מעשר. maaser. All of that makes sense. One
other I guess point within that sort of logic framework is it
was asked yesterday about בכור, bechor, not the בכור bechor of a
firstborn animal but the פדיון בכור, pidyon bechor, which also doesn't have
קדושה, kedusha, the פדיון בכור pidyon bechor of a child or of
a פטר חמור peter chamor of a donkey, which does not have
קדושה, kedusha, and there the רמב"ם Rambam says, I sort of responded
to Michael this way without remembering the רמב"ם, Rambam, but I checked
the רמב"ם Rambam and he actually says that all of the בכורים
bechors in one category, so logically, so since the בכור bechor of
the animal is limited to the male כהנים kohanim because it's a
קרבן, korban, therefore the same is true about the פדיון בכור. pidyon
bechor. All of that makes sense. What? He also says that? Okay,
whatever. All of that makes sense and it's basically drawing the lines
with things with קדושה kedusha that are the תורה Torah emphasizes male
כהנים kohanim and other things where the women or כהנות kohanos or
לויות leviyos could have status, for the first time we're sort of
seeing this, not by virtue of them being part of their father
male כהן's kohen family, but in terms of their own personal status
when it's not one of those things. The interesting thing is that
the רמב"ם Rambam says in a very surprising claim that has everybody
astounded, he says that not only do you give זרוע לחיים וקיבה
zeroa l'chayayim v'keiva and ראשית הגז reishis hagez to the כהנת, kohenet,
you even can give תרומה terumah and תרומת מעשר terumas maaser and
חלה. challah. Now, that is very surprising because those types of things,
it's explicit in the תורה, Torah, and if that wasn't enough the
רמב"ם Rambam rules that if the female
כהנת kohenet is married to a male ישראל, Yisrael, she does not
entitled to תרומה, terumah, she cannot eat it, it can only be
eaten when she is still single and part of her father's family.
And basically the way the commentators reconcile it is they say that
they must say okay רמב"ם Rambam is talking when she's not married.
But even if that's true that the רמב"ם Rambam is talking that
she's not married, it still is a surprising extension of
the רמב"ם, Rambam, that the רמב"ם Rambam is saying that even when
it comes to areas of things gifts that have קדושה kedusha like
תרומה terumah and חלה, challah, okay, if there's not a problem in
terms of their eating of it because they're unmarried, they're entitled to
it on in their own on their own on their own sake.
So you could directly according to the רמב"ם Rambam and people are
astounded by this because it seems to be against a lot of
other גמרות, Gemaros, but the רמב"ם Rambam seems to be saying that
a person could directly give his תרומה terumah to a female כהנת
kohenet as long as she was not married to a male ישראל
Yisrael which would prevent her from eating it.
Or a woman לויה? leviyah?
Or מעשר maaser to a woman לויה leviyah the רמב"ם Rambam definitely
says, but there it does not have קדושה. kedusha. But even a
female even the even a כהנת, kohenet, as long as she's not
married to ישראל Yisrael she is directly entitled to the תרומה. terumah.
Well you can't give her the תרומה terumah and what not anything
related to קרבנות korbanot and you can't give her the תרומה terumah
and בכור bechor and so on and you can't give her the
תרומה terumah if she's married to ישראל. Yisrael. But it's quite fascinating
the way the רמב"ם Rambam extends those categories.
Okay, yes, you know, based on what I was saying yesterday, it
really means no sense to exclude other women when the גמרא Gemara
did it, but we don't know why. It didn't make sense to
exclude זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroa l'chayayim v'keiva based on פסוק pasuk anyway.
Right, so the רמב"ם Rambam
so basically the רמב"ם Rambam picking up a little bit on your
point says that the fact that the פסוק pasuk there mentions זרוע
לחיים וקיבה zeroa l'chayayim v'keiva and תרומה terumah in the same פסוק,
pasuk, so your argument
was... ...a woman who is a כהנת *kohanet* and a woman who's
a לויה *leviya*. So I just wanted to sort of summarize that.
Let's start with today's דף *daf*, the bottom of קל"ג עמוד ב
*kuf lamed gimmel amud bet*, where it says the following. Wait, hold
on.
I don't know if we did really the very end of the.
We did, we didn't do the very bottom, so starting at the,
near the bottom. So it says like this.
One minute. איבעיא להו *ibaia lehu*. The ראש *rosh*. איבעיא להו *ibaia
lehu*, one, two, three, five lines from the bottom. איבעיא להו *ibaia
lehu*. They asked the question. If a כהן Kohen *kohen* says, הראש
שלך וכולו שלי *harosh shelcha vechulo sheli*, excuse me, הראש שלך וכולו
שלי *harosh shelcha vechulo sheli*, ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael* says to a כהן
Kohen *kohen*, you get the head and I get the rest of
it, מהו *mahu*? I'm sorry, did I get it the reversed? I
got it the reversed, excuse me. The כהן Kohen *kohen* says to
the ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*, you keep the head and I'll keep the
rest of it. Okay, so now the ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael* gets the
head. In the head is the tongue and the cheek and whatever
and the jaws. Does he have to, all he gets from the
animal is the head. Does he have to give at least the
מתנה matana. *matana* that's in the head? Does he have to give
at least the jaw and the tongue? Whose animal is it? So
it's the כהן Kohen *kohen*'s animal. He's selling the head to the
ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*. So from that head, does the ישראל *Yisrael* have
to give the one מתנה *matana* that's present in that head? הראש
שלך וכולו שלי מהו *harosh shelcha vechulo sheli mahu*? What's the story?
בתר חיובא אזלינן *batar chiyuva azlinan*? Do we go where the obligation
is, meaning where that מתנה *matana* exists? וחיובא גבי ישראל הוא *vechiyuva
gabei Yisrael hu*? And that's in the ישראל *Yisrael*'s portion, it's in
the head. או דילמא בתר עיקר בהמה beheimah. אזלינן *o dilma batar
ikar behema azlinan*? Or do we say we go where by the
main בהמה beheimah. *behema*? ועיקר בהמה דכהן הוא *veikar behema dekohen hu*?
And the main בהמה *behema* belongs to the כהן Kohen *kohen*. So
this is the reverse of the case we had yesterday. Yesterday we
had that a כהן Kohen *kohen* owns one percent of the head
or one percent of the stomach, and that's enough to exempt you.
A partial ownership of the כהן Kohen *kohen* of that מתנה *matana*.
Now we're asking the mirror image. The ישראל *Yisrael* owns only a
tiny bit, only a little, the part, he owns it a hundred
percent, but he owns only the part that has the מתנה *matana*.
Is that enough to create an obligation, or does the obligation only
come if you own the whole cow or what's considered the עיקר
*ikar* cow? And of course, how do you define at what line
do you define עיקר *ikar*? Fifty-one percent, this half, that half? But
whatever, the question is, is even owning just that piece enough to
obligate you? So let's take a look. תא שמע *ta shema*, come
and hear. עובדי כוכבים וכהן שמסרו צאנם לישראל *ovdei kochavim vekohen
shemasru tzonam leYisrael*, a non-Jew or a כהן Kohen *kohen*, both of
whom their animals are exempt, they gave over their sheep to a
ישראל *Yisrael* לגזוז *ligzoz*, to shear, פטור *patur*, he's exempt from giving
the ראשית הגז reishit hagez *reshit hagez*. Okay, because he is not,
why? Because again, it goes by who owns the animal. They own
the animal even though the Israelite is doing the shearing, but nevertheless,
it's the animal of the כהן Kohen *kohen* and you're exempt.
Wait, it's the animal of the כהן Kohen
*kohen*, even though this is his. It doesn't, that's what פטור *patur*
means.
No, I'm saying, but why is he giving it to him to
shear?
He's hiring him to shear.
Oh, just to get rid of it because of שבוטא *shibuta*? No,
not to like give it to him.
Right. Right. Okay. Now, הלוקח גז צאנו של עובד כוכבים פטור מראשית
הגז *halokeach gez tzo'no shel oved kochavim patur mireshit hagez*. Let's say
not that you did the act of shearing, let's say you just
purchased the shearing of the sheep. So now you own the wool,
you purchased the wool, you do not have to give the first
of the shearings. And it says why? וזה חמור בזרוע ובלחיים ובקיבה
יותר מראשית הגז *veze chamur bizroa uvelchayim uvekeiva yoter mireshit hagez*. There's
a greater stringency in such a case by זרוע לחיים וקיבה Zroa
Lechayaim Vekiva, *zroa lechayim vekeiva* and the ראשית הגז *reshit hagez*. By
the ראשית הגז *reshit hagez*, just owning the shearings is not enough
to obligate you, whereas by the זרוע לחיים וקיבה Zroa Lechayaim Vekiva,
*zroa lechayim vekeiva*, just owning the portion that has those gifts implicitly
is enough to obligate you. Okay, so by the ראשית הגז *reshit
hagez* you don't, it's only if you own the whole animal and
you shear it, but by the זרוע לחיים וקיבה Zroa Lechayaim Vekiva,
*zroa lechayim vekeiva* even if you own just that portion. And the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, שמע מינה בתר חיובא אזלינן שמע מינה *shema
mina batar chiyuva azlinan shema mina*. You see it does not go,
at least by זרוע לחיים וקיבה Zroa Lechayaim Vekiva, *zroa lechayim vekeiva*,
by who owns the whole animal, it goes by who owns just
the portion that has those gifts. And if you have an ownership
of that portion, you have to give the gifts even though the
main animal is not yours. By ראשית הגז *reshit hagez* it's different,
you have to own the whole animal. Yes.
I guess what I'm not understanding is, forget the בתר עיקר בהמה
*batar ikar behema* or not, but it would seem to me, like
if I say, hey, here's the head, I'm giving to you the
מתנה *matana* in it. Why are we,
if it's the כהן kohen, *kohen*'s animal, I'm saying the head is
yours, then to me it would seem that he's relinquishing the מתנה
*matana* in it, because otherwise why say the head is yours? You
know, it just doesn't seem like a gift.
First of all, we're not assuming that this is a gift. This,
I mean, at least the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads all of
this, this is like a sale. But even if it is a
gift, I mean, I don't know, why? Even if it is a
gift, you can't pre-give the מתנות matnot, *matanot*, they're not yours yet
to give. You're, you know, it doesn't even belong yet to this
particular כהן kohen, *kohen*.
And it was, I'm sorry, I thought it was the כהן kohen
*kohen*'s animal, right?
It is. Okay. It's not that it's his זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroa
lechayayim vekeivah, *zroa lechayim vekeiva* to give. Once the ישראל *Yisrael* owns
it, it belongs, you know,
any כהן kohen *kohen* is entitled to it. It's his to transfer
ownership over it, it's not his to determine what the status of
it is as זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroa lechayayim vekeivah. *zroa lechayim vekeiva*.
That's a function of the obligation. Okay, we're actually going to see
that right now in the next case. So let's take a look.
ואם אמר amar, לו חוץ chutz. מן המתנות פטור מן המתנות *ve'im
amar lo chutz min hamatanot patur min hamatanot*.
If a כהן kohen *kohen* sells his cow to a ישראל *Yisrael*
and says to him, I am transferring this to you, but... except
for the gifts, meaning I am keeping to my own ownership זרוע
לחיים וקיבה, zroa lechayayim ve-keivah then the Israelite does not have to
give it. Now that would seem relatively obvious. If he doesn't own
it, how can he give it? But the point is we don't
want to say that the כהן's kohen. stipulation is meaningless and that
the ישראל owns the whole thing and now the ישראל gets to
determine which כהן kohen he gives it to. No, if the כהן
kohen says, "I'm selling to you except for the gifts," then he
keeps, the כהן kohen keeps the ownership of the gifts. Now the
גמרא Gemara will see why this is a חידוש chiddush because of
the case the גמרא Gemara will ask. So let's take a look
at the top of קף למד דלת. Kuf Lamed Dalet. ורמינהו, Veraminhu,
I'll ask you on this. על מנת שהמתנות שלי, Al menat shehamatnot
sheli, let's say a כהן kohen sells the cow to a ישראל
and says on the condition that I keep the מתנות, matnot. that
they're mine. So נותן לכל כהן שירצה, noten lechol kohen sheyirtze, the
ישראל says, "Ha, forget that," he takes the cow and he can
give it to whomever he wants. That stipulation is not binding. Okay,
we'll talk about why in a minute. Now, so but right now
we're focusing on the contradiction. Here it says if he stipulates on
the condition I get to keep the gifts, then his condition isn't
binding. Our משנה Mishnah says if he says, "I keep the gifts,"
it is binding. So what's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara. says,
"על מנת אחוץ קרמיתי?" Al menat achutz karamisi? You're trying to ask
a question from a case of "on the condition that," which is
this ברייתא, Baraita, to our משנה Mishnah which says "excluding," חוץ. chutz
So חוץ שיורא, chutz shiyura, חוץ is a remnant, meaning it's leaving
something over. If I'm selling you the cow with the exception of
the זרוע zroa? לחיים lechayayim וקיבה, it means I'm not transferring ownership
of the זרוע zroa. לחיים lechayayim וקיבה, so obviously that's binding. I
can transfer ownership of most of the cow and not on the
rest. That's our משנה, Mishnah, that works. על מנת לאו שיורא, Al
menat lav shiyura, על מנת al menat is not holding something back.
על מנת al menat is saying, "I'm selling you the whole cow,
but there's one stipulation. The stipulation is when it comes time to
give זרוע zroa לחיים lechayayim וקיבה, you give it to me." That's
different than saying, "I'm not selling it to you." That's saying, "I'm
giving it to you." Okay, so that's why it's a different case.
Now, okay, let's accept that it is a different case. Why does
that stipulation not work? You, Bobby, bought this cow from me, she
agreed on the condition that you give me the מתנות. matnot, So
when it comes time to give the מתנות, matnot, better keep her
condition. And תוספות Tosafot goes even further, and if you don't keep
your condition, the whole sale should be nullified because I only sold
it to you on that condition. So some ראשונים Rishonim say in
principle that's true. Bobby does have to give me those, give me
that. That was the condition. But the Rabbis said we're not going
to let you satisfy that. You know why? Because basically it's like
the case we had before when the כהן kohen is not supposed
to go around and demand the gifts. So this is playing around
too much. You're trying to insist that you get them as the
gifts. But you know what? The whole nature of the giving of
the gifts is that Bobby should get to decide which כהן kohen
to give it to, and the כהן kohen is not supposed to
come and demand it and insist and certainly exclude other כהנים. Kohanim.
So one way of understanding this is that it's a rabbinic issue,
that technically she should satisfy that condition, but we tell her don't.
Okay, another way of understanding that is, and this is the ריטב"א's
Ritva way, he says, "No, you know what? It actually depends on
how you articulate it." If I say to Bobby, "On the condition
that you give me the זרוע zroa? לחיים וקיבה," that's a condition
and she has to satisfy it, she has to give it to
me. But I didn't say that. Look at what I said. I
said, "On the condition that they're mine." So "they're mine" is not
demanding any action from Bobby. It's like saying, "On the condition that,
you know, the sky is orange." So it's like it's a meaningless
statement. I'm making a claim of fact, "on the condition that they're
mine," not on the condition that you give it to me. Right,
so the way the ריטב"א Ritva says, he says it's like you
just sputtered nonsense and therefore we ignore it. See, which is not
as interesting הלכתית, halachically, but he says it as not the precision
of the way that it's phrased.
But it sounds to me that you're saying that on the condition
that you recognize that I have control, that they belong actually to
me.
Right, so it
sounds, doesn't sound such nonsense.
Right, so if understood that way, that's essentially saying that like, right,
so then it maybe is, and
but it's
factually incorrect because it doesn't belong to me. At most...
That's the issue really.
Right, so that's what I mean. You say that they're mine, but
it's not yours. It doesn't belong to you. At most, maybe I'll
give it to you, but it doesn't belong to you. Right, so
but the point is if you took that to the logical extreme,
you would say, "Okay, so your condition wasn't met and therefore the
sale didn't go through." So there has to be a way where
we just dismiss the whole condition because we say
it was one of entitlement.
Well, that is it, and that really is the first point, which
I think is the more satisfying explanation, which is the Rabbis won't
allow this game playing. Right, that makes the כהן kohen approach this
as an entitlement issue, and we're not going to play along with
that.
And when we say Rabbis, we're not necessarily talking about Rabbis who
are כהנים, Kohanim, we're talking about the Rabbis, the thinkers, the thinkers
of the גמרא. Gemara Exactly.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ורמינהו, Veraminhu, I'll
ask you on that. על מנת שהמתנות שלי המתנות שלו. Al menat
shehamatnot sheli hamatnot shelo.
So now we have a ברייתא Baraita that says the opposite. If
the כהן kohen. stipulates on the condition that I get the מתנות,
matnot. we, then the cow is sold and you give him the
מתנות. matnot So גמרא Gemara says, "You're right, that is a debate
of two opinions." בה פליגי, Beha paligi, this is the debate. מר
סבר על מנת שיורא הוא, Mar savar al menat shiyura hu, the
one that says he keeps the מתנות matnot, is not that it
works as a condition, that even though he uses the phrase על
מנת, al menat, what it means is I'm not selling. And therefore,
if he says or he means I'm not selling them, then he
didn't sell them, he kept them. ומר סבר על מנת לאו כשיורו
הוא, U'mar savar al menat lav k'shiyuru hu, the other one holds
no no no, it doesn't mean I'm not selling it, I'm selling
the whole thing, but I'm making a stipulation. And if that's what
you're doing, then we don't let that stipulation go through. We don't
let the, we don't say that the person has to keep their
end of it and actually give them under those conditions and that
framing. Okay, so that's that point in the משנה. Mishnah. And now
we get to the end of the משנה. Mishnah. אמר לו מכור
לי בני מעיה, Amar lo mechor li bnei me'eha, this is basically
a case where somebody goes to the butcher. If he buys all
of the intestines at a flat price, so then it has in
it the קיבה, keivah, the stomach, so then he has to give
it to the כהן, kohen he's got the stomach, and he doesn't
get a discount back from the butcher because he paid a flat
price and he should have known the stomach was there. But if
he bought it by weight, then of course he has to give
it to the כהן, kohen he has the stomach, but he gets
a discount from the butcher because the butcher shouldn't have charged him
for something that he wasn't going to be able to eat and
he actually paid for weight. That's the teaching of the משנה. Mishnah.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara, says on this. So אמר רב,
Amar Rav, said
רב, Rav, לא שנו אלא ששקל לעצמו, Lo shanu ela sheshakal l'atzmo,
אבל שקל לו טבח הדין עם הטבח. Aval shakal lo tabach hadin
im hatabach. This idea that he has to give it to the
כהן Kohen after he bought the intestines is only if he weighed
it out for himself. But if the butcher weighed it out for
him, then the כהן Kohen. can go to the butcher, because then
the butcher basically took this stomach, put it on the scale, charged
the guy ten bucks for it. Okay, so what is the butcher
doing? He's stealing something, he's appropriating something that belongs to the כהנים.
kohanim. So now the כהן Kohen can come and deal with the
butcher. Now there's a little problem here,
he doesn't have the stomach anymore.
Problem is, well, he can get compensation from the butcher. But the
problem is, okay, but didn't we, haven't we been teaching for a
few days מזיק מתנות כהונה, Mazik matnot kehunah, you know, you can't
collect if somebody damages מתנות כהונה, matnot kehunah, it's ממון שאין לו
תובעים, Mamon she'ein lo tov'im, it's money that cannot be, nobody can
demand it. So there are, so the, basically the ראשונים Rishonim say,
the רמב"ן Ramban says two points here. Number one he says, which
is an important point, you'll remember there was one case before where
the king came, the king's officers came and collected the gifts to
pay off debts. And there it actually said you're supposed to compensate
the כהן. kohen How is that different from damaging their things? Because
here you actually have some bottom line benefit that derived to you
from the, from this thing. So there's a, there's a sense that
you have to give that benefit back, it's still sitting there in
your bank account, that benefit. Okay, so there, that's what the רמב"ן
Ramban says happens here. The, the butcher did not just take it
and eat it, the butcher take it, took it and sold it.
So he's now got an extra ten bucks in his bank account
because he sold the stomach. So that's actual present benefit that belongs
to the כהנים kohanim that's in his possession. So therefore he has
to give it back. What about the problem that who's going to
take him to court? ממון שאין לו תובעים, Mamon she'ein lo tov'im,
and who, which כהן kohen can come to him? Anyway, so the
רמב"ן Ramban said it's ממון שאין לו תובעים. Mamon she'ein lo tov'im.
So there you would have to say that, that's what the רמב"ן
Ramban says happens here. It doesn't mean anybody can take him to
court, but it means that he has to compensate the כהנים kohanim
for that. Although it doesn't sound like that, the phrase is הדין
עם הטבח, hadin im hatabach, sounds like you can go to the
butcher. But anyway, that's at least the way the רמב"ן Ramban explains
why it's not the category of מזיק מתנות כהונה mazik matnot kehunah
because he actually has some benefit.
So then who goes to the טבח? tabach?
Well, right, the way the רמב"ן Ramban says it, it means the
טבח tabach has a responsibility. Or maybe it's talking about a case,
for example, of מכירי כהונה, makirei kehunah, that's an easier way to
explain it. Where there was a known כהן kohen. whom it would
go to, so there he might be the one that's entitled to
actually sue the טבח, tabach, yes.
Why can't just any כהן kohen. go up and demand it, just
like any כהן kohen can go up and grab it?
Yes, but that's the whole סוגיא sugya we learned about ממון שאין
לו תובעים, mamon she'ein lo tov'im, that if there's nobody in particular
to file suit, nobody can file suit, right? That was the whole
earlier סוגיא.
sugya. Right, they can't go to court, but if he goes and
demand, asks for it.
That may, okay, so that could be. Maybe הדין עם הטבח hadin
im hatabach means a כהן kohen, can say to him, he can't
force him to court, but he can say to him, hey, please
give me that ten bucks, right?
Like if you had it and he grabbed it.
That, okay, that could be, that the כהן kohen, should demand it
from him without being able to take him to court, right.
And meanwhile the buyer, the seller, they still
have to do whatever the משנה Mishnah says. Yeah, they would still
have to, right, exactly,
what's going on here.
Exactly. Okay, so let's take a look. So that's what רב, Rav,
that's what רב Rav says. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב
אשי Rav Ashi says, אפילו שקל לו טבח הדין עם בעל הבית.
Afilu shakal lo tabach hadin im ba'al habayit. No, even if the
butcher went ahead and measured it out, the only person that has
a responsibility is the purchaser, is the customer. So לימא דרב חסדא
קמיפלגי, Leima d'Rav Chisda kamiflagi, let's say they debate רב חסדא. Rav
Chisda. דאמר רב חסדא, D'amar Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says,
גזל ולא נתייאשו הבעלים. Gazal v'lo nityashu haba'alim.
If somebody stole something and the owners have yet to have given
up hope, because if the owners give up hope, then it's possible
to actually take possession of the object, at least a third party.
But the owners have not given up hope, ובא אחר ואכלה. uva
acher v'achalah. So party A stole it, party B came and ate
it. רצה מזה גובה רצה מזה גובה. Ratza mizeh goveh ratza mizeh
goveh. So if you, the owners have the choice, they can collect
it either from the גזלן gazlan or from the guy who ate
it, because each one benefit, one stole his object, the other one
destroyed his object. That's what רב חסדא Rav Chisda says. דמר אית
ליה דרב חסדא, Demar it lei d'Rav Chisda, one holds like רב
חסדא, Rav Chisda, ומר לית ליה דרב חסדא, umar leit lei d'Rav
Chisda, and the other doesn't hold like רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Now
the question is who is who? It's not very clear and there's
a lot of discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim because once, because if
you look at it, רב... Rav... Rav says deal with the butcher,
right? The other opinion, who was it, רב אסי Rav Assi says
you deal with the customer. So nobody's saying רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
which is that you can deal with either. So the question is
one of these people, רב Rav or רב אסי, Rav Assi, means
even. So the גמרא, Gemara so most ראשונים Rishonim assume that when
רב Rav says you deal with the butcher means you can even
deal with the butcher. Certainly you can go to the guy who
actually has the stomach, but if you can't find him and he's
not around or whatever, you are entitled to go to the butcher
as well because he also stole. That would be רב. Rav. And
רב אשי Rav Ashi would say, רב אסי Rav Assi would say,
again, reject רב חסדא Rav Chisda and say no, you only go
to the person who has the object, you don't go to the
other person who might have, you know, done something against you but
does not now have the object. Okay, that would be, that's the
way the גמרא Gemara suggests. And the גמרא Gemara says, לא, lo,
no, דכולי עלמא אית להו דרב חסדא. de-chulei alma it lehu de-Rav
Chisda. We say everybody in principle agrees to רב חסדא Rav Chisda
that you could go to either. So then what's the issue? והכא
במתנות כהונה נגזלות קמיפלגי. ve-hacha be-matnot kehuna nigzalot ka mipalgi.
Until now we were talking about the status of destroying מתנות כהונה
matnot kehuna and if somebody can demand compensation. Here we're talking about
can you conceptually steal them? Why could you not conceptually steal them?
Because look, if before the כהן kohen has it, there's two questions.
Number one is, does the כהן kohen even own it yet? That
was part of the question of damaging their מתנה. Maybe he doesn't
own it, nobody owns it, I own it until I give it
to the כהן. kohen I have to give it to א כהן,
a kohen, but it's not like it's owned by the class of
כהנים. kohanim. They don't, nobody owns, only I own it until I
give it to them. If that's true, then it's impossible to steal
it. It's possible to do something to obviate my responsibility. If I
sell it, then I'm not going to do my מצוה, mitzvah, but
I didn't steal it, it was mine. That's one idea. The other
idea is maybe it does belong to them, but if it belongs
to them as a class, what does it mean if I steal
something from James? If I steal something from James, I go to
his house or I take, and I steal something, or I take
his wallet out of his pocket. I've removed it from his control
and possession. If this thing is owned by the abstract class of
כהנים, kohanim, how do you exactly take it away from them? What,
because I moved it from here to here? Because I gave it
from me to somebody else? It's not like they were, it was
under their control and I took it out of their control. Well,
if you consume it, but the butcher didn't consume it. So we're
not saying can you be מזיק mazik מתנות כהונה, matnot kehuna, we're
saying can you steal מתנות כהונה? matnot kehuna? How can you steal
something if there's, you know, if there's no significance of it being
in place A as opposed to place B? So that's the question.
Did the butcher, is it possible for the butcher to steal it?
Okay, במתנות כהונה נגזלות קמיפלגי. be-matnot kehuna nigzalot ka mipalgi. מר סבר
נגזלות, mar savar nigzalot, one holds they are stolen and the butcher,
yes, by intentionally giving it to somebody else is like he took
it away from the כהנים kohanim and therefore the butcher can be
demanded to be paid, to pay. ומר סבר אינן נגזלות, u-mar savar
ein nigzalot, it's not stolen. No, it's impossible to steal them and
therefore you only go to the one who is possessing it, not
to the butcher. איכא דמתני לה להא שמעתא בפני עצמה, ika de-matni
la le-hai shemaita bifnei atzma, some teach this independent of our משנה.
Mishnah. רב אמר מתנות כהונה נגזלות, Rav amar matnot kehuna nigzalot, it's
possible to steal מתנות כהונה, matnot kehuna, and רב אסי אמר מתנות
כהונה אינן נגזלות, ve-Rav Assi amar matnot kehuna einan nigzalot, it's not
possible. So by saying it's possible, we are saying two important things
and this is consistent with our ruling of ממון שאין לו תובעין.
mamon she-ein lo tovin. ממון שאין לו תובעין mamon she-ein lo tovin
suggests, seems to say that as soon as I separate them off,
they belong to the class of כהנים. kohanim. Maybe they can't take
me to court, but they belong to the class of כהנים. kohanim.
Once they belong to the class of כהנים, kohanim, it is possible
perhaps to steal it. Maybe not because like I said, you're just
moving it from one place to another, but based on intention and
transfer of possession, it's possible to consider it like you stole. And
therefore that's what רב Rav says and therefore if the butcher intentionally
gives it to somebody else, that was stealing it from the כהנים
kohanim and you can go to the butcher. Who can go to
the butcher is an interesting question. Maybe like James said, the כהן
kohen. can demand it, but the butcher can't, he can't be taken
to court, but at least the כהן kohen. can demand it from
the butcher. Okay, now we go on to our next משנה. Mishnah.
גר שנתגייר והיתה לו פרה. ger she-nitgayer ve-hayeta lo para.
א גר A ger converts, or a non-Jew converts, but א גר
a ger converts, okay, and he had a cow. Now as we
know, if he shechted the cow when he was a non-Jew, he
would not give the מתנות, matnot. it's a cow of a non-Jew.
If he shechted the cow after he converted or somebody shechted it
for him is really the case because it doesn't matter who did
the act of שחיטה, shechita, then he would give the מתנות. So,
נשחטה עד שלא נתגייר פטור, nishcheta ad she-lo nitgayer patur, if it
was shechted before he converted, exempt. משנתגייר חייב, mishe-nitgayer chayav, after he's
converted he's obligated. ספק פטור, safek patur,
if you don't know, he had somebody working on his farm while
he was going off to the מקוה mikveh and converting and he
doesn't know when this cow was shechted. So we say don't, you
don't have to give it. Why not? המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, ha-motzi
me-chavero alav ha-re'aya, and this is the point we've been discussing from
the beginning of the פרק, perek, which is that it's the burden
of responsibility. If you want to sue me, you know, collect from
me civilly and say I owe you money, you have the burden
of proof. So א כהן a kohen wants to go to א
גר a ger and say you have to give the gifts, he
says prove to me that it was shechted after I converted. And
this is interesting because the issue that's been bothering some of you
here is why do we look at this through the civil lens
and not through the מצוה mitzvah lens and say since I might
have א מצוה a mitzvah I should do the מצוה. mitzvah. And
this is always a question when you have something that crosses these
two categories. Like sometimes ראשונים Rishonim say how could you say המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה? ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-re'aya? Why
don't
you say ספק גזל safek gezel and I should give it to
you?
and therefore, and therefore, if in civil court you can't demand it,
then we don't call it ספק גזל. safeik geizel. Then we say
the other guy's entitled. If in civil court you can't demand it,
then we don't say that he has a מצוה, mitzvah, we say
that that will determine the parameters of the מצוה. mitzvah. But this
is actually the question that the גמרא Gemara. is going to ask.
What, should we only look at this through the civil lens of
being able to prove it in court to demand payment? So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara כי אתא רב דימי, Ki
ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אמר, he said, רמי ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן. rami
lei Reish Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish asked the following
question to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan on our משנה. Mishnah. תנן ספק
פטור. Tnan safeik patur. Our משנה Mishnah says that if there's a
doubt you're exempt. אלמא ספיקא לקולא. Alma safeika lekula. We are lenient
because we go by this principle of ממונות. mamonos. ורמינהו, U-reminhu, I'll
ask you on that about another case, not about gifts to a
כהן kohen, but gifts to the poor. חורי הנמלים, Chorei hanemalim, if
you have like, I don't know, an נמלה nemalah is I think
it's some type of a what, weasel or something, whatever it is,
a gopher maybe. What makes holes in a wheat field? Gophers? What?
Prairie dogs? That's what it says it is? Okay, anyway, oh, okay.
Anyway,
you've got these holes in your wheat field. What?
Moles? Okay. You've got whatever it is, you've got these holes in
your wheat field and there's wheat at the bottom of the hole.
So now here's the question: did the wheat fall there before the
harvesting began and therefore the עניים aniyim don't get it, or was
it dropped there in the harvesting and therefore it's לקט? leket? Because
anything that slips through the hands in the harvesting belongs to the
עניים. aniyim. Okay, because it's a hole, it's quite possible that stuff
got dropped there and was forgotten way before you got around to
doing the harvesting. So let's take a look.
שבתוך הקמה, She-betoch hakamah, they're in the middle of the standing wheat,
הרי אלו של בעל הבית. harei elu shel ba'al habayis. Then if
they're in the middle of the standing wheat, you haven't even cut
the wheat, obviously anything in the hole fell off unrelated to the
harvest and is not a gift to the poor. Okay, ושל אחר
הקוצרים, veshel achar hakotzrim, how about stuff in the hole which is
in the area that has already been cut? So there it's possible
that it slipped through their hands and it's לקט. leket. We don't
know when it got into the hole. So it says העליונים לעניים,
ha-elyonim la-aniyim, the top layer is possibly dropped in the harvesting and
therefore the עניים aniyim are entitled to it. התחתונים של בעל הבית,
ha-tachtonim shel ba'al habayis, the stuff on the bottom certainly came much
earlier and was not dropped during the harvest, and therefore the owner
keeps it. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says הכל לעניים, hakol la-aniyim, it all goes to the poor, שספק
לקט לקט. she-safeik leket leket. Any doubt if this is לקט, leket,
if this is a gift to the poor, goes to the poor.
And תוספות Tosafos says it's clear the גמרא's Gemara question here is
not just from רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's even from the תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma. Because the whole debate seems to be do we
consider the stuff at the way bottom of the hole to be
in doubt or not? But everybody agrees that any part of the
grain that we agree is in doubt, then we play it safe
and we give it to the עניים. aniyim. So here you see
we say play it safe and give it to the עניים. aniyim.
We don't say, oh, prove to me that I own it, that
you own it. So what do you do? Do you say if
you have a doubt about these gifts you keep it, or do
you say you give it? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said back
to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, אל תקניטני, al taknitani, do not give
me a hard time with this, don't drain my cup. שבלשון יחיד
אני שונה אותה. She-bilshon yachid ani shoneh otah. I say that משנה
Mishnah is not even רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's just one single
opinion. You know, and therefore we don't really hold of that other
משנה Mishnah about the doubtful לקט leket going to the עניים. aniyim.
דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Beraisa, רבי יהודה בן אגרא
אומר. Rabbi Yehuda ben Agra omer. It's some, you know, very obscure
person, רבי יהודה בן אגרא Rabbi Yehuda ben Agra who makes this
claim משום רבי מאיר, mishum Rabbi Meir, in the name of רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ספק לקט לקט, Safeik leket leket, if you have
a doubt if something is לקט, leket, you give it. ספק שכחה
שכחה, Safeik shikcha shikcha, if you have doubt if it was forgotten,
it was שכחה, shikcha, you give it. ספק פאה פאה. Safeik pe'ah
pe'ah. So he's the one that says that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says all of these doubts go to the עניים, aniyim, but that's
not really the way we rule. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish said back to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אל תשנה
אותה אלא בלשון בן תדא. Al tishneh otah ela bilshon Ben Tada.
What do I care whether you claim it's an obscure opinion or
not? Even if it was in the name, even if it was
בן תדא, Ben Tada, as רש"י Rashi says בן תדא Ben Tada
was like a nobody, it's not a person that we know. It's
like even if it was in the name of Joe Schmo, even
if it was in the name of some foolish person, who cares?
It's a logical position. So don't just dismiss it because you're claiming
it's an opinion of an obscure person. והטעמא קאמר, Ve-ha-ta'ama ka'amar, he's
giving a good reason. דאמר ריש לקיש, De-amar Reish Lakish, because I
say, this is obviously the גמרא Gemara inserting because it was ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish arguing with רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that position makes
sense because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish himself says, so obviously that's the
גמרא Gemara inserting that because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish himself says, מאי
דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's meant by the verse עני ורש הצדיקו, ani
va-rash hatzdiku, deal justice with the poor and the, you know, and
the impoverished. מאי הצדיקו? Mai hatzdiku? What does it mean you deal
justly? Or
הצדיקו hatzdiku also means not just justice, but it also means like
somebody who wins a court case. נקי וצדיק אל תהרוג. Naki ve-tzaddik
al taharog. So, you know, have them succeed, win in their courtings.
אילימא בדינא, Ilima be-dina, if it means that you should incline when
they're actually in court, you should favor them, והכתיב ודל לא תהדר
בריבו, ve-hachtiv vedal lo tehadar be-rivo,
court has to be objective justice, you cannot favor a poor person
in their court case. אלא, Ela, so what does the פסוק pasuk
mean? צדק משלך Tzedek mishelcha צדק משלך ותן לו. Tzedek mishelcha veten
lo. If there's ever any doubt if you owe something to the
poor, weigh in their favor and give from your own money to
the poor, meaning not just a מצוה mitzvah of צדקה, tzedakah, right,
which we know, but if there's here a question about maybe I—the
courts have to deal objectively. But you, if you might owe money
to the poor, it's true if you take them to court they'll
find in your favor, but if you think you might owe money
to them, then give them the money. You know, that's part of
your obligation. Which is actually a fascinating discussion because you know there's
a famous case in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia where one of the
אמוראים, Amoraim, I forget who, had some workers and they broke barrels
and he was taken to court and the judge said, you know
what, technically they have to pay you, but they're poor, they don't
have money, you know, so you basically waive it. Don't make them
pay you. Give even give them money, pay them their wages. So
he said, is this justice? So he said, לפנים משורת הדין. Lifnim
mishurat hadin. So the question is how do you balance the sense
of, okay, but it says don't favor the poor in court. So
in a sense there's these two things going on. In the court,
the court has to be a place of pure justice, to not
favor the poor. But outside of the court, maybe the judge's recommendation,
not as actually a פסק, psak, or what your personal responsibility is,
is that you have to lean towards always being generous towards and,
you know, tipping the scales in favor of the poor. Not what
goes on in court, but your personal responsibility. So therefore that's what
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says. So therefore if you have any doubt
if you owe them the money, if it's ספק לקט ספק פאה,
safek leket safek peah, you should give it to them. So we
still have this question. I think that's a good position. What's פשט
pshat in the משנה? Mishnah? Now obviously the answer could be our
משנה Mishnah isn't dealing with the poor. Our משנה Mishnah is dealing
with the כהן. kohen, And the whole thing we discussed until now
is that the way you give the כהן kohen should be a
way of honor, not a way of treating them as poor. But
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish thinks it's a problem. I believe that in
the case of poor it's a very good position and I want
to know why we don't say it in the משנה Mishnah as
well. So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
says. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says here's the difference.
הכא פרה בחזקת פטורה קיימא קמא בחזקת חיובא קמא. Hacha parah bechezkat
peturah kama kama bechezkat hiyuva kama. The cow existed—started off as being
exempt. It was owned by a non-Jew. Therefore, it's not because any
doubt we don't give. It's specifically there it started being exempt. So
we say that we'll assume that it remains exempt. We go by
חזקה, chazakah, its original status. Here when we come to the wheat,
wheat as a general talk, wheat owned by Jews is in the
category of having to give the gifts to the poor, so we'll
be more strict. So the way רבא Rava now read it is
he's buying into ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. He's saying the basic rule
is not like our משנה. Mishnah. The basic rule is if you
have doubts about any of these gifts, you give them. Our משנה
Mishnah is a very narrow exception because of the case of the
cow started as being exempt. That's רבא's Rava answer. That's not the
way we're going to end. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, והרי
עיסה, Varei issa, you can't say that. You can't say our משנה
Mishnah is the exception. Our משנה Mishnah is the rule. Let's talk
about making dough and giving חלה. challah. נכרי שנתגייר, Nochri shenitgayer, we
have a teaching, right, a משנה. Mishnah. If the dough was made
before the גר ger converted, פטור מן החלה. patur min hachallah. Same
type of teaching as our משנה. Mishnah. מי שנתגייר, Mi shenitgayer, if
it was made into dough after the גר ger converted, חייב, chayav,
you give חלה. challah. ספק, Safek, if you don't know when he
was converting, somebody at home was making the חלה, challah, חייב. chayav.
So you're חייב chayav and there it actually
is—it started with a חזקה chazakah of being exempt, right? The dough
we know started in the possession of the גר. ger. So why
there do we say if you doubt—if you have a doubt you're
חייב? chayav? So here says אביי, Abaye, here's what the real difference
is. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said or רבא Rava said
back to אביי, Abaye, ספק איסורא לחומרא ספק ממונא לקולא. Safek issura
lechumra safek mamona lekula. It makes a difference. By חלה, challah, if
you're obligated in חלה challah and you don't give it, the dough
is טבל tevel and you violate, you transgress by eating the dough.
But in the case of gifts to the poor or זרוע zroa.
לחיים וקיבה, if you don't give it, you're not eating anything wrong.
There's no איסור issur there. It's only a question of who owns
it. So when it's a question of who owns it, then המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hareaya. You prove it, I'm not
going to give it to you. I'm not going to give you
the זרוע zroa. לחיים וקיבה. But if I might owe the כהן
תרומה Kohen terumah or I might owe the כהן חלה, Kohen challah,
then I better give it because if I don't give it, then
I am going to violate—that's an איסור. issur. I'm going to violate
eating טבל. tevel. So that's what he says. So it doesn't explain
the case of the לקט שכחה ופאה. leket shikcha upeah. This seems
to be saying the basic—going back to the point that forget the
לקט שכחה ופאה, leket shikcha upeah, that's an exception. Maybe we don't
rule that way, maybe that's only because of the poor, but it's
not a general rule. The general rule is that when it's איסור
issur you're strict, when it's monetary issues the other person has the
burden of proof. דאמר רב חסדא, De'amar Rav Hisda, so because רב
חסדא Rav Hisda says וכן תני רבי חייא, vechen tani Rabbi Hiyya,
שמונה ספקות נאמרו בגר. shmonah sfekot neemru beger. In these cases of
somebody converted and you don't know whether the thing happened before or
after conversion, he divided it up into eight cases. ארבע לחיוב וארבע
לפטור. Arba lechiyuv ve'arba lepatur. Four you're obligated, four you're exempt. What
are the cases you're obligated? קרבן, Korban, קרבן אשתו, korban ishto, his
wife, actually his wife converted as well. It's not his conversion that
makes the difference. But basically his wife converted and you don't know
whether she was a יולדת. yoledet. Actually it's hard to exactly get
the case because how would she not know whether she gave birth
before or after she converted, but she's... go into the... she gave
birth in the מקוה *Mikvah*? I don't get it.
Right, she's going to the מקוה *Mikvah*, that's the moment of conversion.
I mean, רש"י *Rashi* says, and if גר *Ger* converting doesn't determine
his wife's obligation, רש"י *Rashi* says, if you look at רש"י *Rashi*,
רש"י *Rashi* says, where's רש"י *Rashi*? ספק ילדה כשהיא עובדת כוכבים ספק
משנתגיירה *Safek yalda kesheita ovedet kochavim safek mishenitgayerah*. I'm not exactly sure,
unless she's ממש *mamash* in the process of...
maybe she's giving one of those things giving birth in the water.
I don't get it.
And of him, right, of a female גיורת *giyoret*, yeah. And why
does רש"י *Rashi* say אשתו *ishto*? רש"י *Rashi* should have... why does
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* say קרבן korban, אשתו *korban ishto*? Right, it's
not about the husband, I mean hers. So it's the משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah*... this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s funny. קרבן korban. אשתו *korban ishto*, it's
not קרבן אשתו *korban ishto*, it's קרבנה *korbanah*.
Maybe she decided to convert before she has the child so the
child would be Jewish, so she goes to the מקוה *Mikvah* and
hey, she has the baby.
I understand, you have to consider it, but Rivka's question is right
on the target. Why are we talking about his wife? It's not
about his wife, it's about her. Yeah, so I don't know exactly
how to construct that case. But let's take a look. ספק *Safek*
קרבן אשתו *korban ishto* וחלה *vechallah*, okay,
case of חלה *challah*, you don't know when it was made. ובכור
בהמה טמאה ובכור בהמה טהורה
*Uvechor behemah temeah uvechor behemah tehorah*. His animal firstborn of a donkey
or the firstborn of a sheep. In all those cases you give
it to the כהן kohen *Kohen*. You're strict. Why are you strict?
Because all those are איסור *issur*. If you might have to bring
a קרבן *korban* and you don't bring a קרבן *korban*, you're טמא
*tamei* and you can't eat קדשים *kodshim*. Okay, חלה *challah*, if you're
not giving חלה *challah* and you have to, then the dough is
טבל tevel. *tevel*. בכור *Bechor*, if you have to give it, then
it's קרבן *korban*, it's קדשים *kodshim*. בכור בהמה טמאה *Bechor behemah temeah*,
the donkey is at least forbidden in benefit until you redeem it.
So all of those are איסור *issur*, so if you're not sure,
be strict.
All of those are לחיוב *lechiyuv*. Now, ראשית הגז *reishit hagez* is
the following are for exemption. ראשית הגז והמתנות *Reishit hagez vehamatanot*. So
first the shearings, first shearings, and הזרוע hazroa, והלחיים ve-halechayayim, והקיבה ve-hakeivah,
*hazroa vehalechayayim vehakeivah*.
Those are things which are no איסור *issur*, only a question of
monetary. Does the כהן kohen, *Kohen* deserve... own it or not, deserve
it? ופדיון הבן *Upidyon haben*, redeeming the firstborn male son, human son,
because that's also money, right? There's no איסור *issur* there, there's only
a question of does the כהן kohen *Kohen* get the money? ופדיון
פטר חמור *Upidyon peter chamor*, now that's the case about the status
of the sheep. Let's say you redeem the donkey with a sheep,
okay? Do you have to give the sheep to a כהן Kohen
*Kohen*? So the sheep has no קדושה *kedushah*. So when you... so
the donkey, you have to redeem the donkey, but you don't have
to give the sheep to the כהן Kohen *Kohen* because then you
got rid of the איסור *issur*. Now it's only a monetary issue,
so now you can keep the sheep. So you see the question
is exactly this. If it's monetary, the other person has the burden
of proof. When there's an איסור *issur* aspect, that's your responsibility. Okay,
so... so we still haven't exactly explained why the case about the
gifts to the poor. Maybe we're saying we don't rule that way.
Maybe we're saying that, you know, what I think makes sense based
on ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*'s claim is maybe it's an exception when
it's a difference between the poor versus the כהן Kohen *Kohen*. But
somehow we're bracketing the poor case of the gift to the poor
and we're saying basically when all it is is monetary, you're exempt.
Wouldn't you say that generally the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim* are lumped together
with the poor anyway, usually?
No, but that's the point we were making in the last few
days, that the way you give to a כהן *Kohen* is not
the way you give to the poor. כי אתא רבין אמר כמה
כמה רמי ליה *Ki ata Ravin amar kama kama rami lei*. When
רבין *Ravin* came from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, he said we never
asked from the case of poor to כהן *Kohen*. Somehow we assumed
the poor was a different case. All we were asking about was
that we had one Tannaitic source that had the case of the
poor that said you give it to them, and one said that
you didn't. And there there was a contradiction about those two cases
and there רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said we don't give it to
the poor in that case. The opinion that says you give it
is a דעת יחיד *da'at yachid*, we don't rule like it. So
we end up by saying that when it's not the case of
the poor and all it is is monetary and it's not איסור
*issur*, then even though there's also a question about מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*,
nevertheless we say we deal with it from the monetary lens. המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה *Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah*, from the civil lens, if
you can't prove it, I don't have to give it. And the
only question is if it's an איסור *issur*, obviously you're careful and
you're strict. And the only question is is the case of the
gifts to the poor different that there we would weigh in favor?
That seems to be a debate of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. Now we go on. לוי זרע בקישר *Levi
zara bekishar*, לוי *Levi* planted his field in a place called Kishar.
ולא הוו עניים aniyim? למשקל לקט *Velo havu aniyim lemishkal leket*. And
there was stuff dropped, but there were no עניים aniyim. *aniyim* there.
It was out in the middle of nowhere, somewhere in some wheat
field in Kansas, there were no עניים aniyim *aniyim* around. Right, all
there was around for the next 50 miles were other farmers. So
what do you do with the gift to the poor? It's going
to rot if you leave it there. What do you do with
it? So אתא לקמיה דרב ששת *ata lekamei deRav Sheshet*, he went
to רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, he said to
him, לעני ולגר תעזוב אותם la'ani velager ta'azov otam, *le'ani velager tazov
otam*, you should leave it to the poor and to the stranger.
ולא לעורבים ולא לעטלפים *Velo le'orvim velo le'atalefim*, not... you're not supposed
to leave it to the... like the ravens and the bats. Okay,
so you're not supposed to leave it there to rot, which basically
meant you can keep it. There's no point, you're only supposed to
leave it if the poor can get it. If the poor can't
get it, you have no responsibility. So this is actually a little
bit of the opposite of the other... no, no, so we're going
to see that. A little bit of the opposite of the other
point. The other point was any doubtful thing you
leave. but if the poor can't get it, then you're entitled to
keep it for yourself. Okay. מיתיבי, גמרא Gemara says I'll ask you
on this. אין מביאים תרומה לא מגורן לעיר ולא ממדבר ליישוב. Ein
meivim terumah lo migoren l'ir v'lo mimidbar l'yishuv. Let's say you have
תרומה terumah out in the middle of this wheat field in Kansas.
So you don't have to bring it from your threshing floor to
the city or from the wilderness to a settled area. It's not
your responsibility. Let the כהן come and take it if he wants
it. ואם אין שם כהן, V'im ein sham kohen, but let's say
there is no כהן available and it's just going to rot. שוכר
פרה ומביאה מפני הפסד תרומה. Socher parah umevia mipnei hefsed terumah. Then
you do have to rent a cow and bring it into the
city because you don't want this תרומה terumah to go to waste.
So there you see it is your responsibility to make sure it
doesn't go to waste and you don't keep it. You transport it
and then eventually you're going to give it to the כהן. Now
obviously you can't keep it because תרומה terumah is קודש kodesh and
you would not be able to, but nevertheless it's not saying like
keep it and sell it. It's basically saying you have to preserve
it for the כהן. So why is that different than the case
of the poor? So the גמרא Gemara says, שאני תרומה דטבלא, Shani
terumah detavla, which is what I was saying. אבל לא סגי דלא
מפריש לה. Aval lo sagi d'lo mafrish lah. So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, that's different. You have to be מפריש mafrish תרומה. terumah.
If you're not מפריש mafrish תרומה, terumah, your wheat is טבל. tevel.
So you can say don't give a gift to the poor if
the poor can't get it, but you can't say don't give תרומה
terumah if there's no כהן because your wheat is still טבל. tevel.
Because you'll separate it?
So that's going to be the question.
Okay, one minute. והרי מתנות דלא טבלי. V'harei matanot d'lo tavli. One
minute. There are cases of gifts which don't make טבל. tevel ותניא,
V'tanya, nevertheless we say, מקום שנהגו למלוג בעגלים לא יפשיט את הזרוע.
Makom shenahagu limlog ba'agalim lo yafshit et hazroa. There's a question how
to read this ברייתא, braita, but basically if it's a place where
basically they boiled their young calves as a way of eating it,
then when you go to give the arm to the כהן, you're
not allowed to remove the skin ahead of time because he'll want
to do it with the skin. If למלוג limlog means to boil
it with the skin. להפשיט את הראש, Lehafshit et harosh, the reverse
is true by the head. Even in a place where they normally
skin the head, לא יפשיט את הלחי, lo yafshit et halechi, don't
skin the cheek area, the jaw area before giving it to the
כהן, because we're about to teach that the כהן is entitled to
even like the wool around the jaw, around the skin of the
head, around the jaw area. So anyway, that's just saying that, you
know, the way you have to give it to them, the arm
you have to give with the skin, the arm don't, you know,
basically keep the skin on. Okay, and even if in the head
they normally remove it, keep it on. Now, what's relevant for us
is, ואם אין שם כהן, V'im ein sham kohen, if there's no
כהן around when you take off the זרוע לחי וקיבה, zroa lechi
vekeiva, מעלין אותו בדמים, ma'alin oto bedamim, you figure out its value,
you put that in some escrow account, ואוכלן מפני הפסד כהן, v'ochlan
mipnei hefsed kohen, and you eat it because you don't want the
כהן to lose out. So you don't let it rot, you figure
out its value, you put that money in an escrow account and
you eat it. So here's a case where there's no טבל tevel.
and what it says is you still have to preserve at least
the value of it, not the thing itself which will rot, but
the value of it for the כהן. So why didn't you preserve
the value of the wheat for the עניים? aniyim, Okay, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara's says. שאני מתנות כהונה
דנתינה כתיבא בהו. Shani matnot kehuna denetina ketiva behu. מתנות כהונה Matnot
kehuna are different because it says, and this is exactly the difference
we've been pointing out about the difference between how they're given. By
מתנות כהונה matnot kehuna it says you shall give it to the
כהן. By the gifts to the poor it says לעני ולגר תעזוב
Ta'azov אותם, leave it for them. So give it means you have
a responsibility to ensure that it gets it. תעזוב ta'azov means you
let them come and get it. Okay. So what about תרומה terumah
though? So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא דאתית להכי, Hashta d'atit l'hachi,
now that we've realized this point, תרומה נמי נתינה כתיב בה. terumah
nami netina ktiv bah. That's also why תרומה terumah is different because
that's your question, Michael. Separate תרומה, terumah, but then don't give it
to them. Why do you have to schlep it back? And the
same point, by תרומה terumah it says you shall give the תרומה.
terumah. Basically, תתן לו תרומה, titen lo terumah, anyway, you'll find the
פסוק. pasuk. It says תתן לו, titen lo, anyway. So
anyway,
so what we, so the basic פשט pshat is, is that by
gifts to the כהן, there it's your responsibility to give it. I
think that ties into the whole גמרא Gemara, before about that it's
given in a way that shows their honor, that shows their status.
That's why they receive it in a certain way, you give it
in a certain way, you don't just leave it. They're not supposed
to come and grab. That it's the exact reverse of the עניים.
aniyim, The עניים aniyim. you leave and they come take. Here the
whole point was don't come and grab, wait for me to come
give it to you. So that shows their honor. For the עניים,
aniyim. you're supposed to allow them. Now, by the way, I do
want to make a point that even by the עניים, aniyim it
might be that that's also a sensitivity to the עניים. aniyim Because
when you give it to a כהן, the act of giving can
be shown as acknowledging their status. If I were to give something
to the עני, ani, that's maybe acknowledging their status as being poor.
Right? Nobody thinks it's because they're honored. If I give something to
the עני, ani, it is a handout. It makes them feel bad,
right?
Exactly. And the whole point is, so actually by not giving to
the עני, ani, it is more respecting of their status, not making
them feel sort of identified as עניים. aniyim. So I think the
idea of giving to the כהן and not giving to the עני
ani is exactly to be sensitive to respect their status and not
to, in the case of the עני, ani, to highlight the fact
that they are poor. So that is the difference. But because of
that difference, you don't have to go, you're not supposed to seek
out the עני. ani. And therefore if no עניים aniyim, are going
to come and take it, then you're entitled to keep it for
yourself because you're not, you don't have a responsibility to get it.
to the עני. ani. Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara distinction, which
is interesting; here the עניים aniyim a little bit lose out, and
as opposed to the earlier discussion where they gain, where we sit
in their favor.
You understand the תרומה terumah with a שליח shaliach to Jerusalem, right?
Wouldn't your field be a...
As soon as you separate it, you're done with your ob- you're
done you you remove the status of טבל. But there's a separate
מצוה after you separate it to give it. Okay, and that's what
we're talking about here. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
ואלא תעזוב יתירה למה לי? Ve'ela ta'azov yeteira lama li? So then
why does the תורה Torah say תעזוב ta'azov twice by the gifts
to the poor if not to say that you have to ensure
they get it even if they're not around?
That's for a different הלכה. halacha. לכדתניא, Lechidetanya, like we taught in
the ברייתא, Baraisa, המפקיר כרמו ולשחר השכים ובצרו, Hamapkir karmo uleshachar hishkim
uvetzaro, you you you
renounce ownership over your vineyard and the next morning you get up
and you re- and you you reclaim it and you harvest the
and you harvest the grapes. So it was only הפקר hefker overnight.
Does that get you out of any obligations? Because some types of
things, even if they're הפקר hefker just one minute, get you out
of certain become technical exemptions. So it says חייב, chayav, no, you
still have to give all the gifts to the poor. בפרט ובעוללות
ובשכחה ובפאה, Beferet uve'olelot uveshichcha uvepe'ah, all the various gifts to the
poor. ופטור מן המעשרות. Ufatur min hama'asrot. But what you don't do
is you don't have to give מעשר. ma'aser. מעשר, Ma'aser, if this
stuff was even for one minute הפקר, hefker, then it's exempt from
מעשר. ma'aser.
Even מעשר עני ma'aser ani also? Yeah.
Yes. But because of תעזוב ta'azov that it says by the gifts
to the עני ani of the droppings and the leaving things you
leave, there, as long as it's not הפקר hefker when you when
you harvest it, you still have to give it. So that's what
the תעזוב ta'azov does. So there are ways that the things are
tipped in favor of the עני, ani, but there is one way
that it's not to their favor, which is is if they're not
around, you don't have responsibility.
They don't like to wait for it and that kind of thing
if we do it?
That's a separate question. ההוא סקא דדינרי. Hahu saka dedinari. Now, one
last case about this issue about how does one receive. Okay, so
there was a sack filled with דינרי, dinari, sack filled with golden
coins. Money.
דאתא לבי מדרשא.
De'ata levei midrasha.
It was sent to the בית מדרש, beis medrash, it was a
gift to the ישיבה. yeshiva. All right, anybody any- anybody would like
to would like to sort of follow the example of the גמרא,
Gemara I'll tell you where you can find me for the rest
of today. קדים רבי אמי וזכי בהן. Kadim Rabbi Ami vezachi bahen.
So רבי אמי Rabbi Ami was a ראש ישיבה, rosh yeshiva, he
ran ahead and he he took possession of them. Okay, which the
גמרא just talking about the כהן not supposed to run and grab,
but it was a sack filled with דינרי, dinari, he ran and
he grabbed it. So the גמרא says והיכי עביד הכי והכתיב ונתן?
Veheichi avid hachi vehachtiv venatan? So those שיתן מאצמו, sheyiten me'atzmo,
using the כהונה kehunah as a as an analog. Obviously this is
not מתנות כהונה, matnot kehunah, but the idea is when something is
given, you're not supposed to run up and grab. You know, it's
not respectful for you and it's not proper. You let the you
let it be given to you, and which is the whole discussion
of מתנות כהונה. matnot kehunah. So רבי אמי לעניים זכה בהן. Rabbi
Ami le'aniyim zachah bahen.
He was doing it not for the ישיבה, yeshiva, he was doing
it for the עניים. aniyim And maybe that goes back to the
previous point. For the עניים, it's תעזוב and you're supposed to come
and take it, right? So if is it a handout or is
it a is it a gift of respect? So he decided to
turn it into a צדקה tzedakah and therefore he went and he
grabbed it. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, if you want you could say
אדם חשוב שאני, adam chashuv shani, which is a little bit ironic.
Somebody that's really important, that's different. Then he's entitled to grab it.
Why? You would think the opposite. דתניא, Detanya, we point a ברייתא,
Baraisa, והכהן הגדול מאחיו שיגדלוהו מאחיו. Vehakohen hagadol me'echav sheyigadlohu me'echav. So
the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, so גדול gadol means that he's greater
than his fellow כהנים. kohanim בנוי, Benoy, he's more handsome, בחכמה, bechochmah,
wiser, ובעושר, uve'osher, and more wealthy, that you know you give somebody
that has all המעלות. maalot. So he is the כהן גדול. kohen
gadol. So אחרים אומרים, acherim omrim, מניין שאם אין לו, minayin she'im
ein lo, how do you know if if he's not wealthy but
he's otherwise the right כהן, the right person to be the כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, שאחיו הכהנים מגדלים אותו, she'echav hakohanim megadlim oto,
that his fellow כהנים kohanim have to contribute to him to make
him wealthy, because that's part important for his status. תלמוד לומר והכהן
הגדול מאחיו, Talmud lomar vehakohen hagadol me'echav,
greater than his brothers, so the מ mem is being written from
his brothers. גדלהו משל אחיו. Gadlehu mishel echav. The brothers shall be
the ones that help make him great, they should contribute so that
he becomes wealthy. As we know, people that are wealthy, you know,
carry certain weight and status in the community by virtue of their
wealth and that was important for the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. How's
that relevant for us? So it's saying since the since people have
a responsibility to make him wealthy, so so here as the ראש
ישיבה rosh yeshiva or whatever representing the ישיבה yeshiva which is somehow
seen as the analog for this כהן גדול kohen gadol in an
אדם חשוב, adam chashuv, it's so therefore he's entitled to grab it.
It's still, I have to tell you, I don't really get it,
because there's one question about whether the money should be going to
him and there's another question about how does one take it. The
whole point seems to be for the כהנים kohanim that you don't
grab it, you don't take it. The way that's a respectful way
is that you are given it and you receive it. So I
must say I don't really fully understand the answer, but I think
the first answer of the עניים was fascinating and it played off
of this difference about how do you give to a כהן or
how do you give to let's say, you know, certain types of
causes where the gift is a show of status and how do
you give to עניים and there's a different way in which you
respect sort of the issues or the status in both of those
cases.
You'll ponder the problem in the museum. Right, exactly, when somebody sends...
me the bag of gold coins, I'll let you know how I
decide to act in that case. Okay, so now the משנה Mishnah
says, the final משנה Mishnah. of the פרק, perek, איזו היא הזרוע,
eizo hi hazroa, what is the זרוע? zroa, So I came to
I brought a picture book. Ah, there you go. So here is,
okay, you see this is the זרוע. zroa. It is God takes
us out with a זרוע נטויה, zroa netuyah, so interestingly, it's not
the whole arm, it's the upper part of the arm, these two
bones. This bottom part is the ארכובה. arkuva. You might remember the
ארכובה arkuva keeps on coming up. The זרוע zroa are the two
bones above the ארכובה arkובה going to the shoulder. The לחיים is
the lower jaw all the way to the back, and the קיבה
keivah is one of the stomachs including the tongue. Okay. Yes. So
איזו היא הזרוע, eizo hi hazroa, what's the זרוע? zroa, מפרק של
ארכובה, mi-perek shel arkuva, from the joint of the ארכובה, arkuva, which
is the lower joint, עד כף של היד ad kaf shel hayad
until the shoulder, which is the two upper arm bones. And it's
not just the bones, obviously, it's all the meat on the bones.
והוא של נזיר, vehu shel nazir, that's also when the תורה Torah
says that you have you cook the arm of the ram of
the נזיר, nazir, it's the same זרוע. zroa וכנגדו ברגל שוק. u-kenegdo
baregel shok. And when by, give me that, by a קרבן, right,
you give the שוק, shok, the thigh, and the חזה, chazeh, so
the שוק shok is the similar two bones of the back of
the leg, the hind leg. So these two bones that are above
the, this bottom bone is the ארכובה, arkuva, and the two bones
that go from there to the thigh to the, you know, hip
bone. So that is the that area is the שוק shok that
you give from a קרבן. So it's the parallel, one is the
front, one is the
back. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר omer שוק מפרק של ארכובה עד
סוף הרגל. shok mi-perek shel arkuva ad sof ha-regel. It's only that
middle bone, not the top two bones. ואיזו לחי, ve-eizo lechi, what
is the לחי? lechi? מפרק של לחי, mi-perek shel lechi, from the
joint of the jaw, עד פיקה של גרגרת, ad pika shel gargolet,
and you basically cut back from the beginning of this jaw till
the covering of the esophagus, till the, you know, so you cut
back till the top of the throat and it includes the tongue.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan,
הזרוע זו זרוע ימין. hazroa zo zroa yamin. It's the right arm.
אתה אומר זרוע ימין או אינו אלא זרוע שמאל, atah omer zroa
yamin o eino ela zroa smol, maybe the left? תלמוד לומר הזרוע,
talmud lomar hazroa, the זרוע. מה תלמודא, mah talmuda, what's the derivation?
כדאמר רבא kedamar Rava הירך, hayerech, the opinion of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda way back that the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh was only the
right side. So רבא Rava explained where does he get that idea
that the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is the right side? Because it
says the thigh, המיומנת שבירך, hamiyumenet shebayerech, the right of the thigh,
meaning the more important one. This is the bias towards towards, you
know, righties. My son איתניאל Eitaniel is very offended for all the
lefties in the world. I'm a family that I'm a lefty, דבורה
Dvorah is a lefty, and my two sons are lefties. So
just so every now and then men feel excluded too, we have
the lefties get it from here. Anyway, okay, so.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda had said that it's either, right?
Right, but this is alright, but that was that דרשה. drasha. There
was because there was another way to learn the פסוק pasuk there.
הכא נמי הזרוע המיומנת שבזרוע. hacha nami hazroa hamiyumenet shebazroa. So the
זרוע, the important one, the right one. והלחיים, the jaws, למאי אתא,
le-mai ata,
what's the ה hey coming to do? להביא צמר שבראש כבשים, lehavi
tsemer sheberosh kevasim, what we mentioned before, that they not only get
the jaws, but they even get all of the wool of the
head. So while they're only getting the jaw of the meat, they
get also the ה ha includes the wool around the head. I
don't get it either. ושער שבזקן תישים, ve-sa'ar shebizkan tayashim, and the
goat on of the זקן, zakan, thank you, of the the hair
of the goat of the beard of the goats. והקיבה, hakeivah what's
the ה hey of והקיבה doing? למאי אתא? le-mai ata? להביא חלב
של גבי הקיבה, lehavi chelev shel gabei hakeivah, not just the stomach,
but the fat that's around the stomach, although you couldn't eat it,
you could get הנאה hana'ah from it, you could use it for
like, you know, for like making leather or other types of things
or for burning. וחלב שבתוך הקיבה, ve-chelev shebetoch hakeivah, and the fat
inside the קיבה. keivah. דאמר רבי יהושע, de-amar Rabbi Yehoshua, כהנים נהגו
בהן עין יפה, kohanim nahagu bahen ayin yafah, the כהנים were very
generous when it came to the קיבה, keivah, ונתנו לבעלים, venatnu l'ba'alim,
and they gave the fat back to the owners. So טעמא דנהגו,
ta'ama de-nahagu, that's because that was their practice, they were being generous.
הא לא נהגו, ha lo nahagu, if it weren't their practice, דידהו,
didehu, they would be entitled to not only the stomach but even
the fat in it and around it. Now, a little אגדתא aggadata
to end with. דורשי חמורות היו אומרים, dorshei chamurot hayu omrim, those
that explain it's unclear what the word חמורות chamurot means, רש"י says
by analogy or difficult issues, but anyway, it often means those that
sort of talk more מדרשically, midrash give מדרשic midrash or symbolic explanation
to מצוות. mitzvot. Here's what they said. הזרוע, why the arm and
why the right arm? כנגד היד, keneged hayad, וכן הוא אומר ויקח
רמח בידו. ve-chen hu omer vayikach romach beyado.
So this is פינחס Pinchas because by פינחס Pinchas you have an
arm and you have a stomach. He takes the spear and he
spears it through the stomach of, right, of of
the woman and of the man who's, you know, who are fornicating.
So that's the symbolism. And therefore we know it's the right arm
because of course he was a righty. Okay, so והלחיים כנגד תפילה,
ve-halechayayim keneged tefillah, because פינחס Pinchas prayed. וכן הוא אומר ויעמד פינחס
ויפלל, ve-chen hu omer vaya'amod Pinchas vayifallel, a פסוק pasuk in תהלים
Tehillim
where we're reading it means that he stood up and we're reading
ויפלל vayifallel as ויתפלל, vayitpallel, he prayed. Okay, so he prayed maybe
for God's strength when he was going to do this. וקיבה כמשמעה,
ve-keivah kemashma'ah, the stomach. וכן הוא אומר ואת האשה אל קבתה. ve-chen
hu omer ve-et ha-ishah el kuvatah.
He speared through the woman through her stomach. So this is seeing
the זרוע לחיים וקיבה as because
symbolic for the act of פינחס. Pinchas. You have to admit that
it's a pretty interesting parallel, you know, in terms of certainly the
זרוע. זרוע and the קיבה. keva. I looked at the רמב״ם Rambam
in מורה נבוכים. Moreh Nevukhim. A lot of people don't know this,
but the רמב״ם Rambam in the end of מורה נבוכים, Moreh Nevukhim,
I mean it's a good segment of the book, gives טעמי המצוות,
ta'amei hamitzvot, what the reasons are. So he says why זרוע, לחיים
and קיבה? keva? So he said, well, it's sort of like ראשית
הגז because they represent like prime things of the animal because the
זרוע is like the first appendage, it's like comes out of the
body, there's a sense of first. I don't know, לחיים is on
the head, so he tries to sort of see these as something
that's symbolic, something choice or something first. I don't know if that's
any better. Anyway, the גמרא here certainly makes this parallel. And therefore
we know it's the right because of course פנחס Pinchas would use
his right hand. Let's just finish up. ותנא מייתי
לה מהכא, v'tana maiyiti lah meihacha, the תנא Tanna learns the idea
of right from here. שוק הימין, shok hayamin, the right thigh. אין
לי אלא שוק הימין, ein li ela shok hayamin, I only know
that the thigh that you give from a שלמים shelamim to the
כהן is the right. זרוע מוקדש מנין? zroa mukdash minayin?
How do I know the arm, like by the איל ayil of
a נזיר, nazir, that you give the arm, how do I know
that that's the right arm? תלמוד לומר תרומה. Talmud lomar terumah. It
says you shall give it as a תרומה, terumah, so the extra
word תרומה terumah means that even other things that are gifts, it's
the right. זרוע חולין מנין? zroa chullin minayin? How do I know
the arm that you give by normal שחיטה shechitah to a כהן
that it's the right arm? תלמוד לומר תתנו, Talmud lomar titnu, so
the extra word you shall give means not only is the thigh
coming from the right, but the other parts that you also give
to the כהן are the right, the arm is the right. Last
part of the משנה. איזו לחי מן הפרק של לחי עד הפיקה
של גרגרת, eizu lechi min haperak shel lechi ad hapika shel gargeret,
the jaw all the way to the top of the esophagus. ותניא,
v'tanya, and didn't we teach in a ברייתא, braitah, נוטלה ובית שחיטה
עמה, notla u'veit shechitah imah, that when you take the jaw you
take it with where the שחיטה shechitah takes place? And the שחיטה
shechitah doesn't take place on the top of the esophagus, it takes
place lower down. So that means some of the esophagus is included
in what you give. לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא
רבנן והא רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס. ha Rabbanan v'ha Rabbi Chanina ben
Antigonus. There's a debate about whether the שחיטה shechitah can occur at
the very top of the esophagus. דתניא, d'tanya, מוגרמת פסולה. mugremet pesulah.
מוגרמת, mugremet, which means too high, if it's at the top of
the esophagus it's not good. He, רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס, Rabbi Chanina
ben Antigonus, על מוגרמת הכשיר, al mugremet hichshir, he said it is.
So they all agree that it includes the area of above the
area of שחיטה, shechitah, but the question is how high can you
do the שחיטה? shechitah? At the top of the esophagus or lower
down? איבעית אימא, iba'it eima, if you want, הא והא רבנן, ha
v'ha Rabbanan, both agree that the שחיטה shechitah cannot be at the
top of the esophagus. ומאי עמה? u'mai imah? What does it mean
that you take the בית שחיטה beit shechitah with it? עמה דבהמה.
imah d'beheimah. It doesn't mean you take the jaw with the בית
שחיטה, beit shechitah, you take the jaw and you leave the בית
שחיטה beit shechitah with the בהמה. So it really means that you
don't include the place where it's shechted, you only take the jaw
until the top of the esophagus, from the esophagus down lower, that
remains with the בהמה. הדרן עלך זרוע ולחיים. hadran alach zroa u'lechayayim.